<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Friendly advice to the correctour of the English press at Oxford concerning the English orthographie</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40485</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2215</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6439</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12581433</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12581433</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63778</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40485)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63778)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 960:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Friendly advice to the correctour of the English press at Oxford concerning the English orthographie</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Clavell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Oxford University Press.</term>
               <term>English language --  Orthography and spelling --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63778:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63778:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>FRIENDLY ADVICE TO THE CORRECTOUR OF THE Engliſh Preſs AT OXFORD Concerning the <hi>Engliſh Orthographie.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Clavell</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:63778:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63778:2"/>
            <head>Friendly Advice to the Correctour of the Engliſh Preſs at <hi>OXFORD.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS dutiful and loving Children, who can patiently and wiſely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the changes and decays of their aged Parents, (the common fate of all earthly things) can neither with patience nor ſilence ſee violent hands laid on them, haſtening them to ruine; no more could I, being naturally Engliſh, and a lover of Engliſh, without much trouble of mind, begetting at length this neceſſary Vindication, behold our Mother Tongue ſo preſumptuouſly handled by you, to her ruine, under co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of kindneſs to it.</p>
            <p>I will not deny but you might, in theſe your attempts, have as honeſt an end, as had the daughters of <hi>Pelias</hi> towards him their aged Father; intending nothing worſe, than the renewing and advancing it; as if that were true of you alſo, which <hi>Ovid</hi> hath, of them, <hi>Metam. l.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In manibus veſtris vita eſt, aetáſque parentis.</hi> and the life and flouriſhing of our Language depended wholly on your Art, your Mercy, and Juſtice. Though I confeſs, in one of the <hi>London Gazets,</hi> ſometime ſince printed, I find your, or ſome of the ſame Combination, to be ſo modeſt as to take great <hi>London</hi> into the Plot too, and offer it there to the world, as it is ſpoken, and (as I remember) written in <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Oxford:</hi> coupling <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Oxford</hi> together, as Duck and Mallard by the Bills: or as they are wont to joyn Rabbits together, a fat one, and a lean one, that the one may put off the other the better. And yet this pretty piece of arrogation contrived ſo neatly by the Factors of the Glory of <hi>Oxford,</hi> I find to have ſucceeded ſo unhappily already, that a late Comedian in his <hi>Wits,</hi> forbeareth not to cenſure ſuch Projectors, as ſuch <hi>who take apride in writing of falſe Engliſh:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it was ſuppoſed and intended men ſhould believe it was true, becauſe they writ it ſo. And if you would know why <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Oxford</hi> muſt be the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Rule of writing and ſpeaking pure, reformed Engliſh, it is (as was intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) that <hi>Oxford</hi> alone might give Law in this caſe, and <hi>London</hi> look on and admire that Univerſity, in compariſon of which, (as your publick Orator <hi>D.S.</hi> once ſolemnly ſaid) <hi>Cambridge</hi> was no better than a Country School. But if that had been all, ſomething had remained good to her; but now, of late, it is in danger to looſe that little reputation, as not being able to teach true Engliſh, for want of a Theatre.</p>
            <p>But how great accrument of glory is due to you, for your late Emendations of our Language, I ſhall endeavour briefly to declare, if not prove, as well from ſome general Obſervations of other Languages, againſt which you of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend; as alſo more particularly againſt the moſt certain conſtitution of our Engliſh Tongue. For I think, I may here cry out with <hi>Druſius</hi> in <hi>Geneſis</hi> firſt, v. 5. <hi>O divina Grammatica, quam ſaepe ineptiunt, qui te negligunt, &amp; contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunt!</hi> And ſo again, Deut. 26.6. <hi>O divina Criſis, quam mulia ſaepe ignorant qui te ignorant! O divine Grammatical learning, how do they often trifle, who neglect and contemn thee? O heavenly Critical learning, how many things do not they know, who are ignorant of thee!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might begin from the Tower of <hi>Babel</hi> to ſhew what affronts you put upon the 75 Languages into which the once united Maſs of Tongues mouldred, as <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus Stromat. p.</hi> 338. noteth: but S. <hi>Hierome</hi> upon S. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi>'s Goſpel, chap. 26. ſays into 72, according to the number of Nations di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed, over which (ſay the ſame Authors) ſo many Angels do preſide; to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63778:3"/>which he ſuppoſed Chriſts words to relate, when he mentioned the 12 Legions of Angels ready to aſſiſt him at his call: But chiefly I forbear, becauſe I am, in truth, no ſuch Antiquarie, nor Linguiſt, as to be able to diſcourſe of them, and becauſe both Mr. <hi>Selden de Synedriis, l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>n.</hi> 3. and <hi>Buxtorf de Linguae Hebraeae Origine, Theſ.</hi> 10, 11, 12. have learnedly diſcourſed on that Subject. But if we will give any credit to <hi>Goropius Becanus</hi> in his <hi>Hermathema,</hi> or our own <hi>Verſtegan,</hi> we ſhall find that the <hi>Saxon-Dutch</hi> Language, (of which ours is a principal Dialect) is a Mother Tongue, and moſt ancient, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo venerable, as to be valued for that, and to be ſerved by Moderner Tongues, and not, contrary to its <hi>Genius,</hi> to be modelled and corrected by ſome which inferiour in age, would pretend to be ſuperiour in perfection, whereas in truth, it is the moſt ſignificant in it ſelf, moſt elegant in its compoſitions, and conciſeſt of all Languages under Heaven; and therefore well might have ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved our turn ſtill, without the corrupt mixtures (which ſome call Graces) of other Languages.</p>
            <p>There is a common Fate which purſuing all ſublunary things to decay and confuſion, ſeizes on Tongues and Languages too, as <hi>Horace, de Arte Poetica,</hi> hath taught us, thus.
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Sylvae foliis pronos mutantur in annos</l>
                     <l>Prima cadunt: it a verborum vetus interit aetas.</l>
                     <l>Et juvenum ritu florent modo nata vigentque</l>
                     <l>Debemur morti nos noſtraque—</l>
                  </lg>
               </q> And not only do the Languages vary ſo, as out of one common Root of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, (as moſt ſay) or Chaldee (as ſome think) the vaſt diverſity of words do riſe (though no doubt but many words after the diviſion of Tongues were by the ſeparated Societies of People invented, having no dependence at all upon the moſt Original Tongue) but diverſity of pronunciation alſo, of the ſame Language will prevail, and create ſubdiviſions thereof. The Oriental Tongues, as Hebrew, Chaldee, Syriack and Arabick, are generally Guttural in their ſpeech: but thoſe of <hi>Aſia</hi> the Leſs, with the <hi>European</hi> Greeks are moſt Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine; uſing the palate of the mouth, in ſpeaking: as alſo do the Italian and Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nards, as <hi>Hiſpalenſis Iſidore,</hi> (himſelf a Spaniard) teſtifieth. Yet if he had lived in theſe days, his judgment might have been queſtion'd, ſhould he ſo ſpeak. For at this day, <hi>Italy</hi> alone differs much according to the principal Inſtruments of ſpeech. For the Florentines, now a days, are almoſt as much Guttural as the Arabians, or our Welſh. The Venetians uſe the Palate of their mouth moſt: The Neopolitans pronounce moſt from their teeth, and the Genoeſe in the lips: the Romans retaining the beſt <hi>decorum</hi> in pronunciation. All which I mention, not out of any vain pretence to Criticalneſs in thoſe Languages, but to draw from thence this concluſion directly appoſite to the very late humour ſtirring: For though theſe Tongues thus vary, none that I have heard of, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eſpecially no better Judges than we by and by ſhall ſhew you to be) have preſumed to alter the Language in writing, as they have involuntarily in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation: but this is a Spirit of Arrogance worthy of <hi>Oxford</hi> only.</p>
            <p>But I doubt not you will waft me over into <hi>France,</hi> to learn new faſhions there, or bring them over to <hi>England,</hi> for grand Preſidents of mending Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages here: but I muſt crave leave to deny both the Authentickneſs of ſuch a Precedent, and the prudence of the writers after ſuch Copies: both becauſe it is a vain and phantaſtical Nation, light, and variable, and can never ſee when they are in a good condition; and becauſe the Ape is always more ridiculous in his imitations, than is he whoſe actions are ſo natural, (as daily change is to the French) as to become him well enough: and alſo becauſe I find that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of theirs lately taken up, of writing as they ſpeak (which ſurely you aim at in ſome meaſure) condemned by one of their own Nation, when it ſcarce peeped out of its ſhell, a fitter judge of Language than they who advanced
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63778:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>that vain deſign. For of it thus writeth <hi>Seigneur Des Accords,</hi> in his <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narures;</hi> or Collections Recreative, fol. 3. <q>De noſtre temps quelques un ſe ſont volu <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fforcer de innover in l'eſcriture Francoiſe: l'autorite des quelles eſt trop petit, &amp; les raiſons trop foibles pour ſe fair croir. Et quand cela ſe pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roit (ſe que je n'accorderay jamais) ſi eſt ce que pour inſtereſt du poublick, il ne devoit ſouffrir. Car il adviendroit, que d'icy a cent ans, il ne ce trouvoit plus perſones qui peut lire toutes nous eſcritures; ny protocoles de Notairs: &amp; per un pernicieux conſequence, feroit accroyer, quils auroient eſcrire de mots ou jamais n'avoient penſe.</q> Which I preſume thus to Engliſh: <hi>Every one now a days takes upon him to innovate our writing: whoſe Authority is too ſmall, and their reaſons too weak to give them credit. And if this ſhould take effect, which I will never believe; if it were only for the publick interest, it were not to be endured. For it may happen hereby, that an hundered years hence, we ſhould ſcarce find one, who ſhould be able to read all our writings, no not the firſt draughts of our Regiſters: and ſo by pernicious conſequence, men ſhall be made to believe, that they wrote ſuch things as they never imagined.</hi> And if it be ſaid yet, That it be comes us to conform our Language nearer to tranſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine compoſitions of words: I ſhall preſume to tell you, I cannot agree to them in ſuch counſels: and that upon the ſame reaſon <hi>Scotus</hi> gave, why water is cold, and fire hot, <hi>quia hoc est hoc, &amp; illud eſt illud;</hi> i. e. <hi>water is water, and fire is fire:</hi> and French is French; and Italian is Italian; and Engliſh is Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh: and ſo let it be for me; whatever it may be for you.</p>
            <p>But, methinks I hear that phanatical reaſon from you, uſed by Sectaries for the reforming our Religion, contrary to Law and Reaſon, <hi>viz.</hi> What needs ſo many ſuperſluous letters cumber our words, and make our Language too hard and burdenſorne to many well meaning Subjects of his Majeſty, who are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to live in peace? And why ſhould we be troubled with ſo many Letters which profit nothing, but hinder good people, who would gladly Write true En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, but they cannot command their ſpirits to conforme to ſo many ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of ſpelling? And therefore ſurely, it were far better, for the better uniting his Majeſties good Subjects in one plain and eaſie way of writing true Engliſh, to lay a ſide theſe dividing, inneceſſary formes of ſpelling words. And beſides all this, there was an excellent Act of Parliament drawn up by (then) Mr. <hi>Birch:</hi> in his Ingenious Catalogue of Books under the Rebellious Government, which ſeems to be very neceſſary now; and put in practice in <hi>Oxford,</hi> without the conſent of the King, or either Houſe of Parliament, the Theatre giving autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity enough to it: and it is this, as it there ſtands, Claſſis the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cond, Act. 36. word for word. <hi>An Act in behalf of all Clerks and Notaries, whereby they have libertie, to Shorten, daſh, or contract any words, for avoiding of falſ? Engliſh, as heretofore in Latine.</hi> To this ſo great authority, (the beſt vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of you) I confeſs I want an anſwer, unleſs I may ſay it hath been of late years, antiquated. And for your tender, ſcrupulous, and aggrieved ſpirits with the ſuperfluous rites of ſpelling Engliſh, I leave you to be eaſed by the many, large, and elaborate Diſputations publiſhed for the uſe of Weak Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters; ſuch as I take you to be, as will competently appear from what now follows.</p>
            <p>Firſt that you ſeem not to have conſidered, your liberty of reforming, is repugnant to the general cuſtomes of all known Languages to me, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve to you alſo, though much more a Linguiſt than am I as Diſſenters de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands are to all known Religions: For Firſt, All Languages have ever allowed ſome Conſonants and ſome vowels in words to ſtand idle, and <hi>Quid fient</hi> (as they ſpeak) unleſſe perhaps ſerving for <hi>Euphonie,</hi> or gracefullneſs of pronun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation, or to direct us to the fountain from which they ſpring? And who, that hath but taſted of the Oriental Tongues, can be ignorant of <hi>Sheva Quieſcant</hi> in the beginning, middle, and end of words very oft? but I do not mean as if
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63778:4"/>ever it began a word, but as the firſt ſyllable of a word. But this is one quarrel which you pick with the Engliſh tongue, that it hath <hi>e</hi> often, and ſometime<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other letters, not ſounded and therefore not to be ſuffered: denying it the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon law or libertie of all languages, moſt unreaſonably, and by conſequence, unlearnedly: And thus you (for example) you alſo ſtrike out <hi>p</hi> in the midle of a word at your pleaſure; and contrarie to your own rule of conforming En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh to other Languages: and for <hi>temptation,</hi> you will have <hi>temtation;</hi> and for <hi>redemption, redemtion:</hi> that you may alienate them the farther from the Latine Tongue, from whence they ſpring: to which ſometimes you would reconcile us.</p>
            <p>Next, you ſhew your ſelf a great enemie to our Engliſh Dipthongs; in which our tongue exceeds moſt, if not all Languages; which you therefore judge as unbecoming it, as <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the Tyrant did the golden beard of <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> which he ſacrilegiouſly took away, becauſe his Father <hi>Apollo had</hi> no beard at all: as <hi>Tully</hi> tells us <hi>De natura deorum.</hi> So ſurely very undecent do you e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem it, that we, (as Learned Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> in his Engliſh Grammar hath noted before me) ſhould have eleven Dipthongs, and other Languages have not above half ſo many. For in truth I ſee no reaſon but we ſhould allow 12 Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thongs in our Tongue, and why <hi>io</hi> in words derived from the Latine Tongue, ſhould not be ſo accounted. Examples of all which theſe may be: <hi>ai,</hi> as <hi>faith, aid, maid: ea,</hi> as <hi>lead, read, fear, heaven: ie,</hi> as <hi>field, friend, liev,</hi> ſignifying choice; as when we ſay <hi>I had as liev,</hi> and <hi>I had liever,</hi> which vulgarly is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted into, <hi>I had lether,</hi> or in ſtead of that, is uſed, I <hi>had rather,</hi> which is quite another word deſcended from the Saxon word <hi>rath,</hi> ſignifying, <hi>ſoon.</hi> But to proceed, <hi>eo,</hi> as <hi>people; ei,</hi> as <hi>heir, their, eu, Feud, Eunuch: oa, Oak, choak, coaſt: ou, loud, ſouth, thou,</hi> and moſt, or all our words derived from Latine Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantives; as <hi>Doctour, Amour, Ardour:</hi> which it hath pleaſed you to change very arbitrarily into, <hi>or.</hi> In <hi>oi, moiſt, ſoil: ui,</hi> as <hi>guilt, quilt: io;</hi> as <hi>mention, nation, viſion,</hi> where the four laſt letters make but one ſyllable pronounced in Proſe, or Verſe, unleſs when the Verſe requires a <hi>diaereſis,</hi> or ſeperation; as the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines do; ſometimes, writing <hi>pictaei</hi> for <hi>pictae.</hi> The French Grammars tell us, that Tongue hath one Tripthongs as <hi>beautè,</hi> which alſo our Tongue hath, writing <hi>beautie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now when a Language is thus ſetled by conſent, for private heads to break the Rule, under pretence of meliorating the ſame is to bring in confuſion: and to make our writing as different as our pronunciation, which will be no ſmall inconvenience, and is ſuch a violence, void of prudence, that none of thoſe we call the Learned Languages, would ever endure, though ſubject to the like diſcrepancie in ſpeaking and writing as ours is: and no learned men, before this Age, (and it is well if they of this Age be learneder then other men) did ever attempt to reforme a Language in this manner: ſo that it may ſeem ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an emptie affectation to ſeem ſome bodie; than really to be ſo. But if that humour be prevalent in them, it were a great deal better they ſhould remove their Preſs from <hi>Oxford,</hi> to <hi>Smolensko,</hi> or ſome noted Citie between the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ovites</hi> and <hi>Polacks,</hi> whoſe Slavonian or Sarmatian Language is ſo crouded thick with conſonants, which cannot all be heard, they ſeem extremely to need and call for ſuch a <hi>Procuſtes,</hi> as <hi>Oxford</hi> hath; who may lengthen or ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten words, as they agree beſt with his Cratch. But the truth is, that a funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental errour againſt the Analogy of all Tongues, hath mightily abuſed you, to conceive that Pronounciation ſhould be any certain Rule of Orthographie, when as it ſelf is very uncertain: and your reformations many of them do not anſwer the true pronunciation: ſo that I ſcarce know where to have you, in ſuch inconſtancies; who ſometime would have pronuciation a Rule of ſpelling; and ſometimes your (not the common) ſpelling a Rule of true pronunciation. But poſſibly you had before you for a Precedent, <hi>Auguſtus Ceſar,</hi> (For ſurely you
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63778:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>muſt imagine your ſelf above the condition of a ſubject, who undertake to give us Laws of writing and ſpeaking our own tongue) of whom <hi>Suetònius</hi> in his Life writes, <hi>Videtur potius corum ſequi opimonem qui perinde ſcriben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, ac loquendum exiſtiment. He ſeemed to be of their opinion, who conceive we ought to write as we ſpeake.</hi> And therefore <hi>Suetonius</hi> himſelf (as it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows) wonders very much, at what others wrote of him, that he was ſuch a ſevere and punctual obſerver of Orthographie, that <hi>Legato Conſulari ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorem dederit, ut rudi &amp; indocto, cujus manu Ixi, pro Ipſi ſcriptum ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madvertit:</hi> i. e. He turned a Deputy-Conſul out of his Office, and put ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into his room, becauſe, under his own hand, he wrote <hi>Ixi</hi> for <hi>Ipſi,</hi> as an ignorant illiterate Fellow. From hence it may be moſt probably gathered, that, in thoſe days, <hi>Ixi</hi> was vulgarly pronounced for <hi>Ipſi,</hi> and yet <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> (as well learned, as wiſe) would not ſuffer ſuch emendations, upon ſuch grounds. And the difficulty of reconciling <hi>Auguſtus</hi> his oppoſite practiſes, is not ſo great as it ſeemed to <hi>Suetonius.</hi> For either we are to underſtand the Emperour of Phraſe, rather then Words or Orthographie, as if he avoided the finery or gallantry of Language, unbecoming the Majeſty of ſo great a Prince, and choſe to write plainly (but yet truly) as he ſpake; or elſe, he might look upon the correction of a Language, as a matter above the capacity of perſons, who are as ſubject to the Laws of ſpeaking, as they are of living, under their Sovereign <hi>Tiberius Ceſar,</hi> deſired and endeavoured to add but one Letter more to the Roman Alphabet, but common conſent and cuſtome would not allow it him: Brave, but certainly not grave ſpirits are they, who, at their private pleaſures ſhould ambitiouſly become the Authors of adding or taking away a letter from a word: as will appear now we come to a more particular examination of your alterations made in our Mother Tongue, in ſome few, of many inſtances to be given.</p>
            <p>I confeſs I am not much verſed in the Engliſh Prints at <hi>Oxford.</hi> I have only ſeen a Bible in <hi>Quarto</hi> there printed; but never read one Page in it, as being unwilling to read ſo ſacred a Volumne, when I ſhould be ſure to meet with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny errours, though but Grammatical. But I have been told by a principal Bookſeller in <hi>London,</hi> that men would not buy that Impreſſion, for your. Hete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodox ſpelling, found therein. I am better acquainted with two other Books printed at <hi>Oxford;</hi> the one named, <hi>The Ladies Calling,</hi> the other <hi>The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Tongue:</hi> in which I do not pretend to inſtance in half the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cographies</hi> there found, but ſuch few as the entrance into them offers to every eye: And leſt you ſhould looſe time in teaching us new words, the very firſt word, and that of the Preface, gives us a notable inſtance of your extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry faculty of diviſing words, never heard of before in our Language: where you ſay, <hi>The Editor to the Reader.</hi> And ſurely it was your modeſty ſo to write; for had you ſaid, <hi>The Editor</hi> to the <hi>Lector,</hi> it would have made a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er noiſe, and procured you greater admiration amongſt women, to whom you write. And yet again you went ſo far, that if (as it often happens) bad Latire words make good Engliſh ones; the Ladies, to whom you write, might ſcar you had greater mind to eat them, than inſtruckt them. But if you had pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have ſuffered it to ſmell of the Engliſh Tongue, ſo far as to have written <hi>Editour,</hi> a ſmall glimſe had been given to a good gueſſer, to know your mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: but writing <hi>Editor,</hi> none unlearned above the Engliſh Tongue, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an tell whether the word be Hebrew, Arabick, or Ethiopick, for it comes as near them as Engliſh. I dare ſay, never an Engliſh man in <hi>London</hi> ever ſpake or wrote ſuch a word, though you once promiſed ſuch a form of the Engliſh Tongue; was ſpoken in <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Oxford.</hi> I pray be pleaſed to turn to your Dr. <hi>Hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi>'s Animadverſions on that Ingenious and Learned Gentleman, Mr. <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond Leſtrange</hi> his Hiſtory of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, and not fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, you ſhall find a few Verſes againſt ſuch boiſterous wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, which will
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63778:5"/>fit your foot exactly: but I think not requiſite here to repeat them. But the truth is, that ever ſince Mr. <hi>Holliday</hi> ſet your ſtile at <hi>Oxford,</hi> a <hi>Gog,</hi> (who in his latter days both diſtaſted and deteſted his own ſtrains) you have but too commonly and juſtly deſerved the cenſure of <hi>Auguſtus Ceſar:</hi> of whom <hi>Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius</hi> in his Life, chap. 86. thus writes; <hi>M. Antonium quidem, ut inſanum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepat, quaſi ea ſcribentem, quae mirentur potius homines, quam intelligant. He reproved</hi> Mark Antony <hi>as ſenſleſs, for ſo writing as if he would have men rather admire, than underſtand him.</hi> It may be, you will ſet <hi>Tully</hi> againſt <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> of whom <hi>Quintilian,</hi> or <hi>Cornelius Tacitus,</hi> or (as others lately think) <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſala de Claris Oratoribus,</hi> thus writes, <hi>Satis conſtat, nec Ciceroni quidem detrectatores defuiſſe, quibus inflatus &amp; tumens, necſatis preſsus, ſupra mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum exultans, &amp; ſuperfluens, &amp; parum antiquus videretur.</hi> 'Tis true, <hi>Cicero</hi> might ſeem to ſome detractours, flatuous, and ſwollen, and not ſufficiently compact, but flaunting, ſuperfluous, and modern: but we cannot ſay he devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed new words, or, as great a Maſter of the Latine Tongue as he was, that he took upon him to add, and leave out Letters in writing, as he liſted: or that he ſtuffed every page with Metaphores, Hyperboles, Synecdoches, and ſuch like, as not to ſay according to the common Proverb, <hi>A man cannot ſee wood for trees,</hi> but a man cannot ſee trees for leaves: nor what ſtuff the garment is made of, for colours. But <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in his Rhetorick gave us no ſuch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, but on the contrary rather, that ornament of Speech ſhould be rather <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> than <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: ſawce, than meat; but I ſee forrein Cookery is crept into the Engliſh Tongue, as well as ſet on our Tables: by vertue of which, we find in an egregious Sermon publiſhed by a bold Divine very near <hi>Oxford,</hi> to have dreſſed up luckie Treaſon, ſo handſomely, that it may make a man in love with it, and hate only the Oratour.</p>
            <p>But I am not now to meddle with thoſe offences; but with the petty Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of clipping the Kings Engliſh, and adulterating his Language; which ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber men were not wont to do formerly. Very few (I confeſs) are the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions you make inſtead of corrections, by additions, yet one I ſhall name in your <hi>Government of the Tongue,</hi> as <hi>Sciencies</hi> for <hi>Sciences,</hi> generally received; becauſe ſurely it was not neer enough the Latine Tongue before: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, hereafter by the ſame reaſon we muſt alſo write <hi>Inſtancies,</hi> and <hi>experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies,</hi> and <hi>ignorancies,</hi> for our uſual, <hi>Inſtances, experiences,</hi> and <hi>ignorances:</hi> Nay, we muſt go through the work of reforming, and in the ſingular number alſo, write <hi>Sciencie</hi> for <hi>Science,</hi> and <hi>inſtancie</hi> for <hi>inſtance,</hi> and <hi>experiencie</hi> for <hi>experience.</hi> For our Language (as I ſhall ſhew by and by) requires nothing more, generally to the making a Noun Subſtantive plural, of a ſingular, but the addition of a ſingle <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I am to touch your alteration by way of defect: and firſt, in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of words, where firſt I note your great ſpite, or skill againſt Dipthongs, generally turning words derived from the Latine, into the Latine Tongue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: as <hi>Editor,</hi> (intended for an Engliſh word, but ſpoil'd in the making) for <hi>Editour;</hi> and writing <hi>color</hi> for <hi>colour;</hi> and <hi>humor</hi> for humour. And the vein being on you, you could not ſtop there, but venture to do the like to words properly Engliſh; as <hi>Neighbor</hi> for <hi>Neighbour;</hi> and <hi>mold</hi> for <hi>mould.</hi> And no better deal you with <hi>ea,</hi> dipthong; writing <hi>leſur</hi> for <hi>leaſure,</hi> and <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur</hi> for <hi>meaſure;</hi> contrary to the French, whom ſometimes you pretend to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; who write <hi>meaſure,</hi> as we do. And what can be the reaſon hereof, we know not, beſides your, <hi>Sic volo, ſic jubeo.</hi> And I wonder alſo we muſt have in your <hi>Government of the Tongue, Inveihing</hi> for <hi>inveighing;</hi> unleſs your al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns more to the Latine: And for the ſame reaſon ſurely, you print, <hi>exemt</hi> for <hi>exempt;</hi> and <hi>preſumtion</hi> for <hi>preſumption;</hi> and <hi>redemtion</hi> for <hi>redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> do you not? No ſurely: here the Latine Orthographie is not good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, but you fear you ſhould make Ladies mouths ſtand awry, if they ſhould
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63778:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>pronounce true Engliſh. And with greater confidence yet, you deſert the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, in writing <hi>Supercede</hi> for <hi>Superſede.</hi> But perhaps you firſt ſaid in the Latine Tongue, concerning that word, to be there, <hi>Supercedo,</hi> and not <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſedeo,</hi> by which preſumptuous acts of yours, the true Etymologie of words may ſoon ſuffer much: as it hath in the very name <hi>Oxford,</hi> which is moſt generally ſuppoſed to take its derivation and denomination from an Ox and a Ford; but falſely: though the very Armes of that Place would prove ſo much; and a more modern writing of that name, by interpoſing one ſyllable in the middle, would ſtrengthen the vulgar errour; for the greater glory of it; as <hi>Oxenford:</hi> that ſo, as they ſay, that aſcribe much to the power of numbers, <hi>Achilles</hi> overcame <hi>Hector</hi> (otherwiſe as good a man as he) becauſe <hi>Achilles</hi> his name conſiſted of three ſyllables, and <hi>Hectors,</hi> but of two; ſo <hi>Oxford,</hi> becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Oxcuford,</hi> with three ſyllables, ſhould ſo far overpower <hi>Cambridge,</hi> that of a Famous Univerſity, it ſhould become a Countrie School. But the <hi>Rebus</hi> or Hieroglyphick ſeems quite to be ſpoild, by the more true Etymologie given us by Mr. <hi>William Slater,</hi> an ingenious Antiquarie, in his Marginal note, on his <hi>Votum,</hi> before his <hi>Palae-albion,</hi> thus writing <hi>Ousford, the true interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Oxford; ſo called of the river Ouſe running by it.</hi> So that whoever will have an Ox for the Armes of <hi>Oxford,</hi> muſt rather fetch it from the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Univerſity of <hi>Athens,</hi> to which it anciently belonged: but that falling into decay, the Beaſt left that place, (and travailing I know not which way) till it came to <hi>Calice,</hi> did wade or ford over to <hi>Dover,</hi> and from thence paſſed ſtrait to <hi>Ousford</hi> and made it <hi>Oxford,</hi> afterward <hi>Oxenford;</hi> the ſame year that the Virgin <hi>Maryes</hi> houſe was carried from Ieruſalem to <hi>Loretto:</hi> making it the famouſeſt Univerſity in <hi>Europe,</hi> where I leave it.</p>
            <p>I come next to ſhew how you have injuriouſly and ſhamefully <hi>docked</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh words, by taking from the latter end of them. And here firſt, whereas it was moſt uſual to leave the vowel <hi>e</hi> at the end of a word, as <hi>Quieſcent,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to many ancient and modern Languages, but eſpecially for the great uſe, informing and declining words, beſides the foreſaid Euphonie; now a dayes, with leſſe judgment than boldneſs, that muſt be removed. Firſt all our Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives ending in double <hi>ſs,</hi> never wanting <hi>e</hi> after them, muſt now ſtand without: becauſe (forſooth) pronunciation is ſecure without it: And therefore now <hi>bleſſedneſs,</hi> and <hi>wickedneſs,</hi> and <hi>gueſs</hi> and <hi>bleſs</hi> muſt want <hi>e</hi> which they had formerly; and upon much better reaſon than it is denied them now: And ſo the verbs <hi>love, have, live,</hi> and ſuch like, muſt content themſelves with threee letters now as <hi>lov, hav, liv,</hi> to the overthrow of that general rule in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming our Engliſh verbes, whoſe <hi>Tenſes</hi> and <hi>Perſons</hi> were generally carried on with the addition of <hi>s</hi> or <hi>th,</hi> or <hi>ſt,</hi> or <hi>d</hi> only joyned to the Firſt perſon Singular: as <hi>I love, I have, I knowe, I live,</hi> beget the ſecond perſon <hi>thou lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, thou haveſt</hi> or contractedly, <hi>haſt; thou knoweſt,</hi> and <hi>thou liveſt.</hi> And ſo the third perſon; <hi>He loveth, he liveth, he knoweth:</hi> And ſo in the Preterim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect Tenſe, <hi>I loved, I lived, I Followed, thou loveſt</hi> and <hi>know</hi> being here Anomalous. Thus may a man obſerve, that moſt Engliſh words are formed by the addition of the ſaid two letters, and ſometimes, three to the original verb: but now upon this new device, we muſt be conſtrained to make an <hi>e</hi> on purpoſe to diverſifie our perſons: which alſo muſt be done in nowns ſubſtantive, when we would of <hi>ſingular,</hi> make them <hi>plural.</hi> Formerly, and more compendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and ſimply, we made all Plurals by onely <hi>s</hi> added: as <hi>bonds, words, lights,</hi> &amp;c. and therefore ever after a double <hi>ſs</hi> in the laſt ſyllable, was added an <hi>e</hi> ſtanding, not (as many imagined) alltogether uſeleſs; but in readineſs to receive another <hi>s</hi> when there was an occaſion to uſe the plural number: as <hi>wickedneſse,</hi> made the plural, <hi>wickedneſſes:</hi> and <hi>Exceſſe, Exceſſes,</hi> and <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, diſtreſſes.</hi> But if a man ſhall write in the ſingular, <hi>wickedneſs</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs</hi> and <hi>diſtreſs;</hi> he cannot make of them the plural number, by adding ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63778:6"/>
               <hi>s,</hi> but muſt be forced to take a whole ſyllable ſo to do, contrary to the common grounds of our Engliſh Tongue, againſt which yet, it ſeems ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of the lateſt to ſpeak, faſhion having ſo far prevailed ever ſince, and ſcarce before the late Rebellion, under <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, when ſome men ſtruck at the ancient eſtabliſhed Lawes of Church and State, others buſying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in murthering or mutulating Engliſh words, which they alſo called <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</hi> I do remember in the Rebellious times to have met with a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie Primer, which would take off the unneceſſarie ceremonies from words; and taught Children to read and write <hi>trubl,</hi> and <hi>battl,</hi> and <hi>duble,</hi> for <hi>trouble,</hi> and <hi>battle,</hi> or <hi>battel,</hi> and <hi>double</hi> very learnedly; and a fit precedent for <hi>Oxford</hi> Preſſe to follow.</p>
            <p>And what ſhould I here mention the innumerable inſolences of that Preſſe in leaving out <hi>e</hi> the termination of words, as in <hi>Calm, Som, Sarcaſm, Preſs,</hi> with which the foreſaid books abound. I adde to theſe ſort of changes, another abſurdity, in taking away conſonants too; as for example, writing there <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolic, Topic, Stomac, Dublick,</hi> in ſtead of the known words <hi>Diabolick, Topick, publick:</hi> or, as ſometimes they were written <hi>Diabolique, Topique, Publique:</hi> but never, but from <hi>Oxford</hi> with a <hi>c</hi> terminating them: unleſs from <hi>France,</hi> where I find them ſo ſpelt; but what have we to do to conforme our Engliſh to their Language? And yet I ſuppoſe as one of Faſhion, rather than ſubſtance, followed them, when you alſo wrot, <hi>vertu</hi> and <hi>valu,</hi> for <hi>vertue</hi> and <hi>value,</hi> as the Engliſh Tongue requires.</p>
            <p>But being almoſt as much tired in writing, as I may ſuppoſe you may be in reading this, I ſhall only mention your Maſterpiec of refining or reforming our Language, in conſtant writing <hi>Tho</hi> for <hi>though,</hi> and <hi>thro</hi> for through in The Government of the Tongue thus, printing the words Pſalm 139. v. 9 <hi>Their Tongues go thro the world;</hi> which if it doth appear to be done with any good judgment and reaſon, beſides your old <hi>Sic volo Sic jubeo,</hi> I am content to ſet down under the ſevere cenſure of a troubleſome quarreller: but if not, I hope you will pleaſe (to prevent a Schiſme in our Language) to return to true Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thographie. I cannot imagine what put you upon ſuch a faileur, beſides a vain deſigne of ſoftning our Language, and ſo to confound the rules of ſpelling, that the weake and ignorant may juſtifie their involuntarie ſlips from ſuch volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie errours as you commit: or from a more generall ground whereby now of late dayes, Libertie of writing is become as reaſonable, as libertie of beleiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and worſhip: And ſo there ſhould remain no ſuch thing as true and falſe ſpelling in the Engliſh Tongue. Or perhaps you conſidering that the vowel and two letters <hi>g, h,</hi> which you rob the foreſaid words of partaking of the nature of aſpirations, you thought it adviſable, to ſpare us our breath, the better to cool our porrage; as I may ſo write, in imitation of you, teaching us to regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late our Pens by our Tongues.</p>
            <p>But I might argue firſt againſt your <hi>tho,</hi> and <hi>thro,</hi> becauſe being but parts, of words, they can ſignify nothing at all, ſtanding by themſelves: as the very firſt page almoſt, of ſome Logicks tell us, ſo that the ſyllables in <hi>domus,</hi> being ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, ſignifie juſt nothing: though both <hi>do</hi> and <hi>muſt,</hi> as entire words, doe. But what ever you may ordain that relique of a word for, you can give us no reaſon why it ſhould retain the ſame force in pronunciation, as when it enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all its letters. For in our Language, Initial letters do varie their value ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their terminations. For inſtance, <hi>Tho</hi> in <hi>though,</hi> is not to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced as <hi>Tho</hi> in <hi>Thought.</hi> For it is manifeſt to any ordinarie obſerver of the Engliſh ſpeech, that <hi>th</hi> hath a double force, ever ſince we loſt the uſe of the Saxon ð, of which you may read ſo much ſpoken by Mr. <hi>Gill</hi> in his <hi>Logono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> in his <hi>Engliſh Grammar.</hi> For there remains ſtill ſo great affinity between the Saxon, or Teutonick (as <hi>Verſtegan</hi> pleaſes to call our Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage) ð, and our <hi>th,</hi> that we ſometimes write ſome words with the one, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63778:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſometimes with the other, without any exception: as <hi>murther</hi> or <hi>murder:</hi> and I know ſome countries in England, where the common people wer wont to ſay <hi>It is very thark</hi> or ð<hi>ark,</hi> in ſtead of <hi>dark;</hi> which I once took to be a greater corruption than in truth it is: therefore you writing only <hi>Tho,</hi> we cannot tell, whether we ſhould pronounce it as <hi>o,</hi> or as <hi>tho,</hi> in <hi>thought</hi> and <hi>thorow,</hi> untill we have taken our horſes and rod to the Oxonian Oracle. For if you ſhould (and upon your own grounds you ought to) write, <hi>thi</hi> for <hi>thigh,</hi> we could not tell whether we ſhould pronounce it as <hi>thie,</hi> or as <hi>thigh,</hi> without recourſe had to the ſaid Oracle. But it ſhould ſeem, the authour of this rare and civillzed way of writing never conſiderd the force of <hi>ugh</hi> cut off by him; which is not ſo aſpirate as he might imagine for ſome countries (and that adjacent to Oxford ſhire) pronounce <hi>though,</hi> as we generally do <hi>cough</hi> and <hi>rough,</hi> and <hi>laugh</hi> and <hi>enough,</hi> as if they were written <hi>Thoff, coff ruff, enuff.</hi> Now would I fain know, whether your <hi>Tho</hi> come, or ought to be ſo pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced: And if ſo, why we may not write <hi>Co,</hi> and <hi>Ra</hi> and <hi>La,</hi> for all that belongs to them. I muſt ingenuouſly confeſs; I being but a ſimple <hi>Davus,</hi> and no <hi>Oedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> cannot underſtand, nor unriddle this; and you being but an <hi>Editor</hi> and not <hi>Cadmus</hi> i.e. a Maſter of Letters or maker of Languages, I am not bound to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev you, though you ſhould tell me your meaning. But there remains one reaſon more againſt <hi>tho</hi> for <hi>though,</hi> which I hope you will believe to be valid, when your ſenſes ſhall convince you: and that is, that in our ancienter En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Tongue, <hi>tho</hi> ſignifies quite another thing from what you intend it: as may appear from <hi>Chauncer;</hi> who uſes it two wayes, But neither of them in your ſenſe. For with him it ſignifies <hi>Then,</hi> and not <hi>Though;</hi> as in thoſe verſes quoted out of him, by his Publiſhers, (I ſhould have ſaid <hi>Editors</hi>) before his works, which are theſe.
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I know that in fourm of ſpeech is change</l>
                     <l>Within an hundreth yeers; and words tho</l>
                     <l>That hadden price, now wonder, nice and strange</l>
                     <l>Think we them; and yet they ſpeak them ſo;</l>
                     <l>And ſped as well in love as men now do</l>
                  </lg>
               </q> Theſe Verſes are made in commendation of the Engliſh Language, even before <hi>Chaucer:</hi> and therefore his offence againſt our auncient Tongue, leſſe excuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; that, contrary to his own judgment, he ſhould endeavour to improve and imbelliſh it, by a number of Latine and French words brought into it, to the loſs of as many, and as ſignificant Teutonique words, and to the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Mother tongue; as <hi>Verſtegan</hi> hath obſerved, and proved againſt <hi>Chau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer.</hi> Yet is this brave Authour more excuſable than many of this age, as uſing that liberty of innovating chiefly in Poetry, where it was evermore allowed. than in Proſe, wherein he is much more ſparing of forrein words. In <hi>The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant of the Roſe,</hi> being a tranſlation of the French Authour <hi>Clopinel</hi> or <hi>Meung,</hi> he about the beginning, uſes <hi>tho</hi> for <hi>then:</hi> and in his <hi>Teſtament in Love,</hi> fol. 301 of his Workes, ſometimes he uſes it for <hi>then,</hi> and ſometimes for <hi>thoſe:</hi> as: <hi>I have (qd I tho) y nough:</hi> for <hi>quoth I then:</hi> And preſently after, he thus uniteth, <hi>I would now (qd I) a little underſtand ſithen all things thus before en not, whether thilking be of tho things.</hi> i.e. of <hi>thoſe things.</hi> Thus he: but you, for <hi>tho,</hi> or <hi>thoſe,</hi> pleaſe to write <hi>thos,</hi> keeping neither to old, nor modern Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thographie, but walking by your ſelf, to the prejudice of the uſual pronuncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is thereby altered. This you doe in the Preface to <hi>The Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Tongue.</hi> And with the like liberty, in <hi>The Ladies Calling,</hi> you write <hi>lest</hi> for <hi>leaſt:</hi> as if you underſtood not the difference between the adverb leſt, and the adjective <hi>leaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But there I end my defence of our Orthographie offended by you; wherein
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63778:7"/>if I have erred, I hope I ſhall be better informed ere long from an Oxford <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, which we may hope to ſee ſuddenly publiſhed there, according to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> beſt Copies there only to be found, eſpecially if Subſcriptions come in plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, anſwerable to ſo weighty a work: that ſo, as according to you, Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridg is but a Countrie School, Oxford may become a Schooldame, to teach us to ſpell, though in that Art ſhe hath been very unfortunate hitherto.</p>
            <p>And thus Sir, end I my weak Advice conceived and declared not ſo much in oppoſition to you, as vindication of our ancient birthrights; in which you have committed ſo many Raſures already, and by the ſame reaſon may proceed to more and greater alterations, till ſome retaining <hi>their old Mumpſimus,</hi> and others following your New <hi>Sumpſimus</hi> of writing, a Babel of confuſion firſt, and then of diviſion be introduced, which may reduce us to another Heptar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie of ſpeaking; others being encouraged by you, to be reforming our Tongue, as well as you: ſo that in proceſs of time, we, now united, may relapſe into that unhappineſs of men, which irrationall creatures are not ſubject too. Who, in all Parts of the earth, underſtand thoſe of their own kinde; as a Lyon, horſe, dogge and hog of Europe or Aſia underſtand their fellowes in Affrica and America, when ever caſually they meet, as well as if they had been alwaies bred toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: which mankinde cannot do, no not after the Famous Univerſal Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter publiſhed for their inſtruction. But all this notwithſtanding, when the Legiſlative power of Language be but halfe ſo well Proved, as it is ill aſſumed by you, you ſhall finde me (to prevent contention) to be not only one of your trueſt Friends, but beſt Subjects.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:63778:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
